<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/blog/feed.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-24T01:24:08+00:00</updated><id>/blog/feed.atom</id><title type="html">InvenTree</title><subtitle>InvenTree is an open-source inventory management system which provides intuitive parts management and stock control. It is at the center of an ecosystem of addins for EDA tools, API wrapper, deeply integrated plugins and 3rd party tools.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">1.1.0 Release</title><link href="/blog/2025/11/02/1.1.0" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1.1.0 Release" /><published>2025-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2025/11/02/1.1.0</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2025/11/02/1.1.0"><![CDATA[<h2 id="110-release">1.1.0 Release</h2>

<p>The InvenTree team is excited to announce the release of version 1.1.0.</p>

<p>This is the first major update since our <a href="/blog/2025/09/15/1.0.0">1.0.0 stable release</a>, and includes numerous new features, improvements, and bug fixes to enhance your experience with InvenTree.</p>

<h3 id="changelog">Changelog</h3>

<p>Major changes are documented in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CHANGELOG.md</code> file in the InvenTree repository.</p>

<p>For a full list of changes made in this release, please refer to the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/releases/tag/1.1.0">release notes</a>.</p>

<h3 id="update-procedure">Update Procedure</h3>

<p>To update to the latest version of InvenTree, please follow the updating instructions provided in the <a href="https://docs.inventree.org">InvenTree documentation</a>. Note that the particular update procedure may vary depending on your installation method.</p>

<h2 id="new-features">New Features</h2>

<h3 id="partial-build-output-complete">Partial Build Output Complete</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10499">#10499</a> adds the ability to complete only a partial quantity of a build output. This allows for finer control over the manufacturing process.</p>

<h3 id="build-output-adjustments">Build Output Adjustments</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10600">#10600</a> allows users to perform stock adjustment actions (count, transfer, etc) on stock items which are in production, i.e. associated with a build output. This provides greater flexibility in managing stock during the manufacturing process.</p>

<h3 id="report-helper-functions">Report Helper Functions</h3>

<p>There have been several additions to the report helper functions, in particular relating to maths and currency operations. Refer to the report documentation for more information on how to use these new functions.</p>

<h3 id="supplier-part-attachments">Supplier Part Attachments</h3>

<p>In <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10724">#10724</a> we added support for uploading attachments against supplier parts. This allows users to associate relevant documents (e.g. datasheets, certifications, etc) directly with supplier parts.</p>

<h2 id="bug-fixes">Bug Fixes</h2>

<p>There have been a significant number of <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pulls?q=is%3Apr%20label%3Abug%20is%3Aclosed%20milestone%3A1.1.0">bug fixes</a> in this release. Thanks to the many community members who have contributed to identifying and resolving these issues!</p>

<h2 id="contributing">Contributing</h2>

<h3 id="new-contributors">New Contributors</h3>

<p>As always we would like to thank all of our contributors for their hard work and dedication to the InvenTree project. In particular, we would like to welcome the following new contributors who have made their first contributions in this release:</p>

<ul>
  <li>@BbqGamer made their first contribution in <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10426">#10426</a></li>
  <li>@hhhapz made their first contribution in <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10485">#10485</a></li>
  <li>@wolfpackmars2 made their first contribution in <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10481">#10481</a></li>
  <li>@neilbeukes made their first contribution in <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10497">#10497</a></li>
  <li>@austenwho made their first contribution in <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10551">#10551</a></li>
  <li>@KaranLala made their first contribution in <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10549">#10549</a></li>
  <li>@akhilsingh-git made their first contribution in <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10722">#10722</a></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="translation">Translation</h3>

<p>Our <a href="https://crowdin.com/project/inventree">translation efforts</a> continue to grow, with coverage increasing across a wide range of languages. We are grateful to all of our translators who have contributed to making InvenTree accessible to users around the world.</p>

<p>If you are interested in contributing to the translation efforts, please visit our <a href="https://crowdin.com/project/inventree">Crowdin project</a> and join the community of translators.</p>

<h3 id="code-contributions">Code Contributions</h3>

<p>Check out our GitHub page for a list of outstanding issues and feature requests. If you are a developer, you can help to contribute to the project by submitting a pull request.</p>

<p>In particular, we are looking for assistance with frontend development, as we work to complete the new user interface and improve the overall UI/UX of the project.</p>

<h3 id="report-bugs">Report Bugs</h3>

<p>If you encounter a bug in InvenTree, please report it on our <a href="https://github.com/inventree/inventree/issues">GitHub issues page</a>. Please ensure that you provide as much information as possible to help us diagnose and fix the issue.</p>

<h3 id="documentation--technical-writing">Documentation / Technical Writing</h3>

<p>If you have experience with technical writing, you can help to improve the InvenTree documentation. We are always looking for help to improve the documentation and make it more accessible to new users.</p>

<h3 id="financial-support">Financial Support</h3>

<p>Sponsorships help to keep this project sustainable, and buys time for the core developers to commit to the project. A recurring or one off sponsorship is a great way to help InvenTree development to continue at full steam!</p>

<p>The work undertaken to keep InvenTree running is done by a very small group of core developers, who do so in their spare time (and are not sponsored by their employers to work on InvenTree). If you benefit from the InvenTree project, please consider contributing to maintain vibrant development of this software!</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://polar.sh/inventree">Polar.sh</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/sponsors/inventree">GitHub</a></li>
</ul>

<p>If you are using InvenTree in a commercial setting, please consider sponsoring the project to help support ongoing development and maintenance. Your support is greatly appreciated and helps to ensure that InvenTree remains a viable and sustainable project for years to come.</p>

<p>If your company benefits from InvenTree, please consider a <a href="https://buy.polar.sh/polar_cl_d7lPAgS9jnW8NDOSWATqdz2gs3wUD1x5M5o7C2rPoAL">one time sponsorship</a> or a <a href="https://buy.polar.sh/polar_cl_UlGc3bUjwB7Vx89dhAY2iF3kUIVFBJC5mJyow4NlJa6">recurring sponsorship</a> to help support the project.</p>]]></content><author><name>SchrodingersGat</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1.1.0 Release]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rolling Stocktake Plugin</title><link href="/blog/2025/10/15/rolling-stocktake" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rolling Stocktake Plugin" /><published>2025-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2025/10/15/rolling-stocktake</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2025/10/15/rolling-stocktake"><![CDATA[<h2 id="rolling-stocktake-plugin">Rolling Stocktake Plugin</h2>

<p>The InvenTree development team has released a new plugin which provides a “Rolling Stocktake” mechanism for InvenTree.</p>

<p>This plugin encourgaes users to perform regular stocktakes of inventory items in a rolling fashion, ensuring that stock levels are consistently accurate without the need for a complete inventory shutdown.</p>

<p>By presenting users with a dashboard widget that highlights stock items that are overdue for stocktake, the plugin helps maintain inventory accuracy and reduces the risk of stock discrepancies.</p>

<p>For more information about the plugin, please refer to the <a href="/SchrodingersGat/inventree-rolling-stocktake">plugin reference</a> or the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/rolling-stocktake-plugin">GitHub page</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>SchrodingersGat</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Rolling Stocktake Plugin]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">1.0.0 Release</title><link href="/blog/2025/09/15/1.0.0" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1.0.0 Release" /><published>2025-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2025/09/15/1.0.0</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2025/09/15/1.0.0"><![CDATA[<h2 id="100-release">1.0.0 Release</h2>

<p>The 1.0.0 release marks a major milestone for the InvenTree project. Not only does it represent an important step in the evolution of the software, but it also introduces a host of new features and improvements that enhance the user experience.</p>

<p>This release includes significant updates to the user interface, performance optimizations, and a range of new functionalities that have been requested by our community.</p>

<p>With <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pulls?q=is%3Apr+milestone%3A1.0.0+">over 600 closed issues</a>, this release is a testament to the hard work and dedication of our contributors. We are excited to see how these changes will benefit users and help them manage their inventories more effectively.</p>

<h3 id="changelog">Changelog</h3>

<p>For a full list of changes made in this release, please see the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/releases/tag/1.0.0">release notes on GitHub</a>. The major changes are documented below, but there are many other improvements and bug fixes that have been implemented as well.</p>

<p>You can also view a <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/compare/0.17.0...1.0.0">full changelog between 0.17.0 and 1.0.0</a></p>

<p>Going forward, we will be tracking major project changes in an internal <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md">CHANGELOG file</a> - this file will be updated with each release, and will provide an overview of the major changes made in each version. This file is in addition to the release notes which are provided by GitHub.</p>

<h3 id="update-procedure">Update Procedure</h3>

<p>To update to the latest version of InvenTree, please follow the updating instructions provided in the <a href="https://docs.inventree.org">InvenTree documentation</a>. Note that the particular update procedure may vary depending on your installation method.</p>

<h2 id="user-experience-survey">User Experience Survey</h2>

<p>In conjunction with the 1.0.0 release, we have launched a <a href="https://forms.gle/a7mFzqZj57FeS7ds9">user experience survey</a> to gather feedback from our community. This survey is designed to help us understand how users are utilizing InvenTree, what features they find most valuable, and where we can improve.</p>

<p>The survey is anonymous and should take no more than 10 minutes to complete. We encourage all users to participate, as your feedback is invaluable in shaping the future of InvenTree. Please consider taking the survey and sharing it with others who use InvenTree.</p>

<h2 id="breaking-changes">Breaking Changes</h2>

<p>As with any major release, there are some breaking changes that users should be aware of. These changes may require adjustments to existing installations, plugins, or customizations.</p>

<p>The most significant breaking changes are documented below, but users should also refer to the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pulls?q=is%3Apr+milestone%3A1.0.0+label%3Abreaking">full list of breaking changes</a>.</p>

<h3 id="user-interface-overhaul">User Interface Overhaul</h3>

<p>By far the largest change introduced in this release is the new user interface. The UI has been completely refactored to use a modern javascript / React framework, which allows for a more responsive and dynamic user experience. This change not only improves the performance of the application but also makes it easier to maintain and extend in the future.</p>

<p>The new UI is now available at the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/web/</code> endpoint - and the old UI has been removed entirely.</p>

<p>Note that old URLs have been remapped to the new UI, so users should not experience any issues with bookmarks or links that point to the old interface.</p>

<p>The general “look and feel” of the InvenTree UI remains consistent with previous versions, but the underlying technology has been updated to provide a more robust and flexible foundation for future development.</p>

<p>While we have made every effort to ensure that the new UI is compatible with existing data and functionality, there may be some edge cases where users encounter issues. We encourage users to report any problems they encounter so that we can address them promptly. In particular, if there are any features that are missing or not functioning as expected, please let us know <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/issues">via GitHub issues</a>.</p>

<h3 id="plugin-system-enhancements">Plugin System Enhancements</h3>

<p>The plugin system has received significat attention in this release. In particular, the plugin system now provides a mechanism for plugins to render their own user interface componenents within the new UI framework.</p>

<p>To this end, we have released an <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@inventreedb/ui">npm package</a> that provides an interface layer for plugins looking to render custom components within the InvenTree UI.</p>

<p>Additionally, we now have a <a href="https://github.com/inventree/plugin-creator/">plugin creation tool</a> which allows users to quickly scaffold InvenTree plugins.</p>

<h3 id="machine-registry-enhancements">Machine Registry Enhancements</h3>

<p>The machine registry has <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10150">received an overhaul</a> which introduces a breaking change for any plugins which implement custom machine registry functionality.</p>

<p>If you have implemented a custom machine registry plugin, you will need to update your plugin to work with the new machine registry system. In particular, the plugin must now implement a new <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MachineDriverMixin</code> class, which provides a consistent interface for interacting with the machine registry.</p>

<h3 id="user-interface-plugins">User Interface Plugins</h3>

<p>This change may require some adjustments for users who have customized their InvenTree installation, particularly if they have created custom templates or plugins that rely on the old UI structure.</p>

<p>Any plugins which have not been updated to work with the new UI will not function correctly, and will need to be adjusted to work with the new interface. This is after we <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8828">removed the old PanelMixin class</a>. This means that any plugins which inherit from the PanelMixin class will now throw an error when loaded.</p>

<p>The new UI plugin system provides a significant amount of <em>context</em> information to the plugins at render time. This means that plugins can now access information about the current user, the current page, and other relevant data when rendering their components.</p>

<p>Additionally, the plugins can access the API directly from the UI, allowing for more dynamic interactions and data retrieval, without the plugin needing to authenticate separately.</p>

<p>This plugin context system was introduced in <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9439">#9439</a>, but further additions and improvements have been made in subsequent pull requests.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@inventreedb/ui">@inventreedb/ui</a> npm package provides full type definitions for the plugin context, making it easier for developers to create plugins that integrate seamlessly with the new UI.</p>

<p>Further, the npm package provieds a set of pre-defined react components which can be reused by plugins.</p>

<p>Scaffolding a UI plugin from scratch represents a significant amount of work, so we have created a <a href="https://github.com/inventree/plugin-creator/">plugin creation tool</a> which generates all of the necessary boilerplate code to get started quickly. This tool can be used to create a new plugin that is ready to be extended with custom functionality.</p>

<p>To integrate seamlessly with the UI, plugin developers should be aware that some <em>core</em> libraries (such as <em>react</em> / <em>mantine</em> / <em>lingui</em>) must be externalized, as they are already provided by the InvenTree UI. This means that plugins should not include their own versions of these libraries, as this can lead to conflicts and unexpected behavior.</p>

<p>Note that this is all handled automatically by the plugin creation tool, so developers should not need to worry about this unless they are creating plugins manually.</p>

<h3 id="notification-plugins">Notification Plugins</h3>

<p>We have changed the way that notification methods can be <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9735">implented via plugins</a>. This change was made to ensure that custom notification methods were able to be loaded and unloaded correctly, and to provide a more consistent approach for implementing notification methods across different plugins.</p>

<p><em>However</em> - this change is <em>not</em> backwards compatible with existing plugins that implement notification methods. Plugin developers will need to update their plugins to use the new notification system in order to continue providing custom notification methods.</p>

<h3 id="builtin-plugins">Builtin Plugins</h3>

<p>The InvenTree project now includes a number of builtin plugins that provide additional functionality and features. These plugins are designed to work seamlessly with the new UI and provide a range of enhancements to the core InvenTree functionality.</p>

<p>Some of these plugins are <em>mandatory</em> - as they are required for the core functionality of InvenTree. These mandatory plugins are installed automatically when InvenTree is installed, and cannot be disabled.</p>

<h3 id="docker-changes">Docker Changes</h3>

<p>Our <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/inventree/inventree">official docker image</a> is now based on a Debian image, rather than Alpine. <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10227">This change</a> was made due to a number of limitations with the Alpine image. The move to a Debian image also brings the docker image closer to the other installation methods, and the devcontainer setup.</p>

<p>Functionally, the new docker image should behave identically to the old image, and users should not experience any issues when updating.</p>

<p>Additionally, we have updated the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9041">supported postgres version</a> in our docker image from version 13 to version 17.</p>

<p>For new installations, this should not cause any issues, as the docker image will automatically pull the latest version of postgres.</p>

<p>For existing installations, this will only make a difference if you wish to update your existing database. Note that our docker image will still support connection to older versions of postgres, so users can continue to use their existing database without any issues.</p>

<h3 id="api-changes">API Changes</h3>

<p>There have been a significant number of changes to the InvenTree API in this release, although the majority of these changes are backwards compatible.</p>

<p>All API changes are <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/blob/master/src/backend/InvenTree/InvenTree/api_version.py">documented in the source code</a>, and users can refer to this file to see the specific changes that have been made.</p>

<p>Additionally, the <a href="https://docs.inventree.org/en/stable/api/schema/">API schema is documented</a> and provides a comprehensive overview of the available endpoints and their parameters.</p>

<h3 id="stock-item-creation">Stock Item Creation</h3>

<p>Creation of stock items via the API has been adjusted, to ensure that the return type is consistent. Now, the return type is always an array of items, even if only a single item is created. Refer to <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9969">PR #9969</a> for more information on this change.</p>

<h3 id="auth-changes">Auth Changes</h3>

<p>We have refactored our authentication framework significantly, both to support the new UI and also to align with modern best practices.</p>

<p>These changes should not affect most users, as we have endeavored to maintain compatibility with existing authentication methods. However, users who have implemented custom authentication mechanisms may need to review their code to ensure compatibility with the new framework.</p>

<p>In particular we have updated our <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/6293">django-allauth framework</a> to align with changes to that library.</p>

<h3 id="bulk-update-mixin">Bulk Update Mixin</h3>

<p>In <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9313">PR #9313</a> we introduced a “BulkUpdateMixin” class which allows some API endpoints to support bulk updates. This mixin can be used to extend existing API endpoints to allow for bulk updates of objects, which can significantly improve performance when updating large datasets.</p>

<h3 id="part-scheduling">Part Scheduling</h3>

<p>The existing “Part Scheduling” feature has been removed in this release, and replaced with a plugin-based solution. This change was made to allow for greater flexibility and customization of the scheduling functionality, as well as to improve performance and maintainability.</p>

<p>Refer to the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/inventree-stock-forecasting">InvenTree Stock Forecasting plugin</a> to replace the old part scheduling functionality.</p>

<h3 id="part-stocktake">Part Stocktake</h3>

<p>The “Part Stocktake” feature has been refactored to make use of the new import/export framework. Prior to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">1.0.0</code>, the concept of “stocktake” referred to two separate concepts:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The ability to provide a snapshot of the current stock levels for a part</li>
  <li>Record historical stock levels for a part</li>
</ol>

<p>These are now split into two separate features:</p>

<h4 id="stocktake-export">Stocktake Export</h4>

<p>Exporting stocktake data is now handled by a provided export plugin, which integrates into the refactored data export framework. This means that the “stocktake” feature is no longer a separate exporter pathway. Refer to the InvenTree documentation for details on how to use the new stocktake export functionality.</p>

<h4 id="stock-history">Stock History</h4>

<p>The “Stock History” feature remains in place, and allows users to view the historical stock levels for a part. This feature provides a detailed view of how stock levels have changed over time, and can be useful for tracking inventory trends and identifying potential issues.</p>

<p>Refer to <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10124">PR #10124</a> for further information on this change.</p>

<h3 id="auto-create-child-builds">Auto-Create Child Builds</h3>

<p>The “auto-creation of child builds” feature has been removed from the core functionality, as it was not configurable and too narrowly scoped to be useful for most users. This feature has been replaced with a more flexible plugin-based solution, which allows users to create custom logic for automatically creating child builds based on their specific requirements.</p>

<p>Refer to <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9574">PR #9574</a> for more information.</p>

<h3 id="remove-django-import-export">Remove django-import-export</h3>

<p>In <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8685">#8685</a> we removed the <a href="https://django-import-export.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">django-import-export</a> framework, which is what was previously used for data import and export. This has been replaced with a <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/issues/8686">custom API driven solution</a> which is more flexible and easier to use. Our new framework runs in the background worker, allowing for processing of large datasets without blocking the user interface (or causing the web server to timeout).</p>

<p>Our data import and export framework has been completely rewritten, and replaced with a custom API driven solution.</p>

<h3 id="stock-return">Stock Return</h3>

<p>The “Stock Return” functionality has been expanded to allow for stock to be returned after having been consumed by a build order. To facilitate this, the API has been refactored to allow for stock returns to be processed more efficiently, and the user interface has been updated to reflect these changes.</p>

<p>However this does represent a breaking change to the API, and users who have implemented custom logic for handling stock returns will need to update their code to accommodate the new API structure.</p>

<p>Refer to <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10132">PR #10132</a> for more information on this change.</p>

<h2 id="new-features--improvements">New Features / Improvements</h2>

<p>There are a number of new features and improvements in this release, many of which have been requested by our community. Some of the most notable changes include:</p>

<h3 id="performance-improvements">Performance Improvements</h3>

<p>We have made significant performance improvements across the board, particularly in areas such as data loading and rendering. The new UI framework is designed to be more efficient, which should result in a smoother experience for users, especially when dealing with large datasets.</p>

<p>The API has also been optimized to reduce response times and improve overall performance.</p>

<h3 id="dashboard">Dashboard</h3>

<p>The new user interface now includes a customizable dashboard that allows users to add, remove, and rearrange widgets according to their preferences. This feature provides a more personalized experience and enables users to focus on the information that is most relevant to them.</p>

<p>This dashboard can be extended with custom widgets provided by plugins, allowing for even greater flexibility and customization.</p>

<h3 id="order-calendar-views">Order Calendar Views</h3>

<p>We have <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8933">reimplemented calendar views</a> for purchase orders, sales orders, and build orders. These calendar views allow users to see their orders in a calendar format, making it easier to visualize and manage their order schedules.</p>

<h3 id="email-enhancements">Email Enhancements</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9608">PR #9608</a> enhances email support capabilities, including plugin support for sending and receiving emails.</p>

<h3 id="order-start-dates">Order Start Dates</h3>

<p>In <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8966">#PR 8966</a> we introduced a new “start date” field for purchase orders and sales orders. This field allows users to specify the date when the order is expected to start processing, which can be useful for planning and scheduling purposes. In <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8915">#8915</a> the “start date” field was also added for build orders.</p>

<h3 id="reporting-printing">Reporting Printing</h3>

<p>Printing of reports and labels is now <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9199">offloaded to the background worker</a>, allowing for more efficient processing of large reports without blocking the user interface. This change also introduces progress tracking for report generation, so users can see the status of their report as it is being generated.</p>

<p>Additionally, reports and labels can now be generated programatically from plugins, allowing for greater flexibility and customization of report generation.</p>

<h3 id="report-merging">Report Merging</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9532">PR #9532</a> introduces a new feature that allows users to merge multiple items into a single report. When generating reports against multiple items, users can now select to render the report as a single document, rather than generating separate reports for each item.</p>

<p>This is selected as an option against a particular report template. Note that it requires the report template to be designed to support merging, as not all templates will be suitable for this feature.</p>

<h3 id="part-parameter-tracking">Part Parameter Tracking</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10023">PR #10023</a> tracks the user who last modified a part parameter, and when it was last modified. This change provides greater visibility into changes made to part parameters.</p>

<h3 id="external-build-orders">External Build Orders</h3>

<p>In <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9312">PR #9312</a> we introduced support for external build orders, allowing users to manage build orders that are fulfilled by external suppliers. This feature is particularly useful for users who need to manage builds that are outsourced to third-party manufacturers or suppliers.</p>

<p>Refer to the <a href="https://docs.inventree.org/en/latest/manufacturing/external/">InvenTree documentation</a> for further information.</p>

<h3 id="bom-enhancements">BOM Enhancements</h3>

<p>Added support for greater flexibility in managing Bills of Materials (BOMs) - refer to <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10042">#10042</a> for details.</p>

<h3 id="build-order-consume">Build Order Consume</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8191">PR #8191</a> adds the ability to partially consume stock against a build order, even if the build order is not yet complete. This feature allows users to consume stock as it allocated, rather than waiting for the entire build order to be completed. This provides users greater flexibility in managing their inventory and build orders, and can help to reduce delays in production.</p>

<h3 id="serial-number-navigation">Serial Number Navigation</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9505">PR #9505</a> adds the ability to navigate between serial numbers in the user interface.</p>

<h3 id="override-global-settings">Override Global Settings</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9718">PR #9718</a> introduces the ability to override global settings via system-level configuration. This allows system administrators to “lock down” certain settings, preventing users from changing them in the user interface. This is particularly useful for ensuring consistency across installations and preventing accidental changes to critical settings.</p>

<h3 id="override-plugins">Override Plugins</h3>

<p>In <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9718">PR #10094</a> we introduced the ability for system adminstrators to mark certain plugins as “mandatory” at the system configuration level. This means that these plugins cannot be disabled or uninstalled by users, ensuring that critical functionality remains available.</p>

<h2 id="bug-fixes">Bug Fixes</h2>

<p>There have been a <em>significant</em> number of bug fixes in this release, with over <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pulls?q=is%3Apr+milestone%3A1.0.0+label%3Abug+">150 tagged PRs</a>.</p>

<p>Note that many of these bug fixes are related to implementation of the new interface, and may not represent issues present in previous versions of the InvenTree software.</p>

<h2 id="contributing">Contributing</h2>

<p>As always, we would like to extend our heartfelt thanks to all of the contributors who have worked tirelessly to make this release possible. The InvenTree project is a community-driven effort, and it is only through the contributions of our users that we are able to continue improving and evolving the software.</p>

<p>There are now <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/graphs/contributors">over 100 contributors</a> to the InvenTree project, and we are grateful for each and every one of you. Whether you have contributed code, reported bugs, provided feedback, or simply used the software, your support is invaluable to us.</p>

<h3 id="new-contributors">New Contributors</h3>

<p>The following developers made their first contributions to the InvenTree project in this release:</p>

<ul>
  <li>@gunstr made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9274</li>
  <li>@reilly-callaway made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9575</li>
  <li>@aluminum-ice made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9638</li>
  <li>@cbenhagen made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9641</li>
  <li>@GoryMoon made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9704</li>
  <li>@willbicks made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9655</li>
  <li>@gitbock made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9775</li>
  <li>@RedEchidnaUK made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9400</li>
  <li>@tristanle22 made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9532</li>
  <li>@sufyan-mukadam made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/9673</li>
  <li>@the78mole made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10107</li>
  <li>@daniil4udo made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10179</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="translation">Translation</h3>

<p>Our <a href="https://crowdin.com/project/inventree">translation efforts</a> continue to grow, with coverage increasing across a wide range of languages. We are grateful to all of our translators who have contributed to making InvenTree accessible to users around the world.</p>

<p>If you are interested in contributing to the translation efforts, please visit our <a href="https://crowdin.com/project/inventree">Crowdin project</a> and join the community of translators.</p>

<h3 id="code-contributions">Code Contributions</h3>

<p>Check out our GitHub page for a list of outstanding issues and feature requests. If you are a developer, you can help to contribute to the project by submitting a pull request.</p>

<p>In particular, we are looking for assistance with frontend development, as we work to complete the new user interface and improve the overall UI/UX of the project.</p>

<h3 id="report-bugs">Report Bugs</h3>

<p>If you encounter a bug in InvenTree, please report it on our <a href="https://github.com/inventree/inventree/issues">GitHub issues page</a>. Please ensure that you provide as much information as possible to help us diagnose and fix the issue.</p>

<h3 id="documentation--technical-writing">Documentation / Technical Writing</h3>

<p>If you have experience with technical writing, you can help to improve the InvenTree documentation. We are always looking for help to improve the documentation and make it more accessible to new users.</p>

<h3 id="financial-support">Financial Support</h3>

<p>Sponsorships help to keep this project sustainable, and buys time for the core developers to commit to the project. A recurring or one off sponsorship is a great way to help InvenTree development to continue at full steam!</p>

<p>The work undertaken to keep InvenTree running is done by a very small group of core developers, who do so in their spare time (and are not sponsored by their employers to work on InvenTree). If you benefit from the InvenTree project, please consider contributing to maintain vibrant development of this software!</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://polar.sh/inventree">Polar.sh</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/sponsors/inventree">GitHub</a></li>
</ul>

<p>If you are using InvenTree in a commercial setting, please consider sponsoring the project to help support ongoing development and maintenance. Your support is greatly appreciated and helps to ensure that InvenTree remains a viable and sustainable project for years to come.</p>

<p>If your company benefits from InvenTree, please consider a <a href="https://buy.polar.sh/polar_cl_d7lPAgS9jnW8NDOSWATqdz2gs3wUD1x5M5o7C2rPoAL">one time sponsorship</a> or a <a href="https://buy.polar.sh/polar_cl_UlGc3bUjwB7Vx89dhAY2iF3kUIVFBJC5mJyow4NlJa6">recurring sponsorship</a> to help support the project.</p>

<h2 id="future-plans">Future Plans</h2>

<p>Our focus over the last year has been on the new user interface, and we are excited to see it finally come to fruition in this release. However, there is still much work to be done, and we have a number of plans for future development.</p>

<p>Check out our <a href="https://github.com/inventree/inventree/issues/">GitHub issues page</a> for a list of outstanding issues and feature requests. We are always looking for help to improve the project, and we welcome contributions from the community.</p>

<p>You can also help by <a href="https://forms.gle/a7mFzqZj57FeS7ds9">completing the user survey</a> to provide feedback on your experience with InvenTree, and help us to prioritize future development efforts.</p>]]></content><author><name>SchrodingersGat</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[1.0.0 Release]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Machine Plugin Refactor</title><link href="/blog/2025/08/21/machine-refactor" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Machine Plugin Refactor" /><published>2025-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2025/08/21/machine-refactor</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2025/08/21/machine-refactor"><![CDATA[<h2 id="machine-plugin-refactor">Machine Plugin Refactor</h2>

<p>In preparation for the upcoming 1.0.0 release, we have made some <em>breaking</em> changes to the machine registry plugin system.</p>

<p>These changes require that any existing plugins which implement custom machine drivers must be updated to use the new plugin system. A new <em>mixin</em> class, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MachineDriverMixin</code>, has been introduced to facilitate this transition.</p>

<p>Plugin developers should refer to the notes below to determine how to update their plugins.</p>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10150">Machine Plugin Refactor PR</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.inventree.org/en/latest/plugins/mixins/machine/">MachineDriverMixin Documentation</a></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="changes">Changes</h3>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/10150">linked pull request</a> makes a number of changes to both the <a href="https://docs.inventree.org/en/latest/plugins/">plugin system</a> and <a href="https://docs.inventree.org/en/latest/plugins/machines/overview/">machine registry</a>.</p>

<p>The most significant of these changes is the introduction of the <a href="https://docs.inventree.org/en/latest/plugins/mixins/machine/">MachineDriverMixin class</a>, which now provides a standard interface for plugins which register custom machine drivers, or custom machine types.</p>

<p>Plugin developers can refer to linked pull request, in addition to the updated plugin mixin documentation, for more information on how to implement this new interface.</p>

<p>The required changes to existing plugins are minimal, and should be straightforward to implement.</p>

<h3 id="example">Example</h3>

<p>As an example, the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/inventree-brother-plugin/">inventree-brother-plugin</a> has been updated to use the new <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MachineDriverMixin</code> class.</p>

<p>Refer to <a href="https://github.com/inventree/inventree-brother-plugin/pull/60">this pull request</a> to see the changes made to the plugin.</p>]]></content><author><name>SchrodingersGat</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Machine Plugin Refactor]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Celebrating 5k Stars on GitHub!</title><link href="/blog/2025/05/22/5k" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Celebrating 5k Stars on GitHub!" /><published>2025-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2025/05/22/5k</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2025/05/22/5k"><![CDATA[<p>The team is rejoiced to acknowledge that the project has now reached 5.000 Stars on GitHub. This and the nearly 1k forks are a reminder of how widely InvenTree has spread in recent years.</p>

<p>We are getting the last setup-improvements and a few smaller features ready to publish the 1.0 release to signify the stability that fellow contributors and users have been experiencing since 2017.</p>

<p>We are always <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/discussions/9073">looking for translators / proofreaders</a>.<br />
Using InvenTree and proud to share? <a href="https://github.com/inventree/inventree-website/discussions/239">Submit</a> to being featured on the website.</p>]]></content><author><name>matmair</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The team is rejoiced to acknowledge that the project has now reached 5.000 Stars on GitHub. This and the nearly 1k forks are a reminder of how widely InvenTree has spread in recent years.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">0.17.1 Release</title><link href="/blog/2024/12/27/0.17.1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="0.17.1 Release" /><published>2024-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2024/12/27/0.17.1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2024/12/27/0.17.1"><![CDATA[<h2 id="0171-release">0.17.1 Release</h2>

<p>We have just released version 0.17.1 which includes a number of patches and bug fixes.</p>

<h3 id="release-notes">Release Notes</h3>

<p>View the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/releases/tag/0.17.1">release notes</a> for more information.</p>]]></content><author><name>SchrodingersGat</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[0.17.1 Release]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">0.17.0 Stable Release</title><link href="/blog/2024/12/17/0.17.0" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="0.17.0 Stable Release" /><published>2024-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2024/12/17/0.17.0</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2024/12/17/0.17.0"><![CDATA[<p>The InvenTree team is proud to announce the release of InvenTree version 0.17.0! This is the most significant release of InvenTree to date, with a huge number of new features, bug fixes, and improvements. We have closed out <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pulls?q=is%3Apr+milestone%3A0.17.0+is%3Aclosed">over 400 pull requests</a> against this release milestone, and received contributions from multiple developers including seven new contributors.</p>

<h2 id="release-notes">Release Notes</h2>

<p>For a full list of changes made in this release, please see the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/releases/tag/0.17.0">release notes on GitHub</a>.</p>

<h2 id="breaking-changes">Breaking Changes</h2>

<p>The following “breaking” changes have been made in this release. Some of these changes will require manual intervention if you are upgrading from a previous version of InvenTree.</p>

<h3 id="samesite-cookie-fix">Samesite Cookie Fix</h3>

<p>Some changes to the underlying Django project have changed the way that samesite cookies are handled. This change illuminated an issue with the way that InvenTree was handling cookies, and this has been fixed in this release.</p>

<p>For existing installs, this change may require intervention from a system administrator to ensure that cookies are handled correctly. Refer to the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8269">pull request</a> for further guidance.</p>

<h3 id="background-worker-and-global-cache">Background Worker and Global Cache</h3>

<p>The background worker process is now forced to use a single worker thread if global caching (i.e. via Redis) is not enabled. This is to prevent multiple background workers from running concurrently and causing issues with the background task queue. This prevents issues with undefined behavior due to race conditions, but may come with a performance penalty for some installations.
Refer to the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8401">pull request</a> for further details.</p>

<h3 id="test-statistics">Test Statistics</h3>

<p>The “Test Statistics” panel has now been removed from the core InvenTree code, and is now available as a <a href="https://github.com/inventree/inventree-test-statistics">separate plugin</a>. This change was made to reduce the complexity of the core InvenTree codebase, and to allow for more flexibility in the way that plugins are managed. Refer to the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8487">pull request</a> for more information.</p>

<h3 id="plugin-installation-improvements">Plugin Installation Improvements</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8503">PR 8503</a> provides a significant improvement to how plugin installation is synchronized when running InvenTree as a containerized application. Additional checksums are now used to ensure that the plugin installation process is more robust. While this change should be transparent to most users, it is a significant change to the way that plugins are installed and managed.</p>

<h2 id="security-patches">Security Patches</h2>

<p>The following security patches have been applied in this release:</p>

<h3 id="dependency-updates">Dependency Updates</h3>

<p>A number of core dependencies have been updated to the latest versions to ensure that InvenTree is running the most secure versions of the software. This includes updates to the Django framework, as well as other core dependencies.</p>

<h3 id="xss-vulnerability-via-malicious-barcodes">XSS Vulnerability via Malicious Barcodes</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8286">PR 8286</a> fixes an issue where a malicious user could craft a custom barcode which could be used to execute a cross-site scripting (XSS) attack. This fix ensures that barcodes are correctly sanitized before being rendered in the InvenTree UI.</p>

<h3 id="all-security-patches">All Security Patches</h3>

<p>Refer to our <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/issues?q=%20label%3Asecurity%20milestone%3A0.17.0%20">GitHub page</a> for a complete list of security patches in this release.</p>

<h2 id="bug-fixes">Bug Fixes</h2>

<h3 id="null-location">Null Location</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8565">PR 8565</a> ensures that the <em>location</em> field of a StockItem is nullified when the item is consumed by a build order or shipped to a customer.</p>

<h3 id="chinese-language-support">Chinese Language Support</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/7878">PR 7878</a> fixes an issue with the Chinese language support in InvenTree.</p>

<h3 id="part-pricing-fix">Part Pricing Fix</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8090">PR 8090</a> fixes a bug which prevented automatic updates of part pricing calculations from working correctly.</p>

<h3 id="other-bug-fixes">Other Bug Fixes</h3>

<p>Refer to our <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/issues?q=label%3Abug+milestone%3A0.17.0">GitHub page</a> for a complete list of bug fixes in this release.</p>

<h2 id="new-features">New Features</h2>

<p>Some of the headline features in this release include:</p>

<h3 id="order-hold">Order Hold</h3>

<p>In <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/7807">PR 7807</a> we added the ability to mark orders as <em>on hold</em>. This additional status enhances the flexibility of the order management system in InvenTree.</p>

<h3 id="testable-parts">Testable Parts</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/7888">PR 7888</a> allows parts to be independently marked as <em>testable</em>. Parts with this flag can have tests associated with them, and can be tested as part of the build process. Note that this flag was previously inherent to the <em>trackable</em> flag, which also allowed parts to be allocated with a serial number. This change separates the two flags, allowing for more flexibility in the way that parts are managed.</p>

<h3 id="user-defined-states">User Defined States</h3>

<p>Custom “states” can now be defined for a number of different objects in InvenTree. This feature was added in <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/7862">PR 7862</a> and allows for user defined states to be used in place of some of the default object states. This will open up new possibilities for customizing the way that InvenTree is used.</p>

<h3 id="sales-order-shipments">Sales Order Shipments</h3>

<p>We have had a major overhaul in how sales order shipments are managed. When allocating stock against a sales order, the allocation no longer needs to point to a particular shipment. Additionally, the new user interface provides a detailed view for each shipment.</p>

<h3 id="date-filtering">Date Filtering</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8544">PR 8544</a> implements API support for date filtering against different endpoints, in addition to UI elements for the new React interface.</p>

<h3 id="failed-task-logging">Failed Task Logging</h3>

<p>Background task failures are now logged to the database, ensuring that administrators can track the status of background tasks more effectively. This feature was added in <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8333">PR 8333</a></p>

<h3 id="dashboard">Dashboard</h3>

<p>The new user interface now supports a configurable dashboard, with multiple widgets that can be added, removed, and re-arranged. This feature was added in <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8278">PR 8278</a>, and also allows plugins to define custom widgets which can be added to the dashboard.</p>

<h2 id="translations">Translations</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://crowdin.com/project/inventree">InvenTree translation project</a> has now received contributions from over 450 community members! This is a phenomenal achievement, and we are grateful to all of our contributors who have helped to make InvenTree available in multiple languages.</p>

<h2 id="new-contributors">New Contributors</h2>

<p>As always, we are grateful to all of our contributors who have helped to make this release possible. In particular, we would like to thank the following new contributors:</p>

<ul>
  <li>@timmyhadwen made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8129</li>
  <li>@fuzeman made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8194</li>
  <li>@skydiablo made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8255</li>
  <li>@webtroter made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8292</li>
  <li>@chris-thorn made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8366</li>
  <li>@jacobfelknor made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8475</li>
  <li>@Mixaill made their first contribution in https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8516</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="100-release-target">1.0.0 Release Target</h2>

<p>This release marks our last minor release before our 1.0.0 release target. In the coming months we will be making some major changes to the InvenTree codebase to prepare for the 1.0.0 release. In particular, this will include a major overhaul of the frontend codebase - you can <a href="/blog/2024/09/23/ui-roadmap">read more about that here</a>.</p>

<p>Our major immediate goals for the project are to ensure that the new user interface is feature complete. This will include ensuring that all existing features are available in the new UI, and that the new UI is fully functional.</p>

<h2 id="support-the-project">Support the Project</h2>

<p>InvenTree is an open-source project, and we rely on the support of our community to keep the project running. There are many ways that you can support the project, including:</p>

<h3 id="code-contributions">Code Contributions</h3>

<p>Check out our GitHub page for a list of outstanding issues and feature requests. If you are a developer, you can help to contribute to the project by submitting a pull request.</p>

<p>In particular, we are looking for assistance with frontend development, as we work to complete the new user interface and improve the overall UI/UX of the project.</p>

<h3 id="documentation--technical-writing">Documentation / Technical Writing</h3>

<p>If you have experience with technical writing, you can help to improve the InvenTree documentation. We are always looking for help to improve the documentation and make it more accessible to new users.</p>

<h3 id="translation">Translation</h3>

<p>We are always looking for help with translations. If you are fluent in a language other than English, you can help to translate InvenTree into your language. Checkout our <a href="https://crowdin.com/project/inventree">Crowdin project</a> to get started.</p>

<h3 id="report-bugs">Report Bugs</h3>

<p>If you encounter a bug in InvenTree, please report it on our <a href="https://github.com/inventree/inventree/issues">GitHub issues page</a>. Please ensure that you provide as much information as possible to help us diagnose and fix the issue.</p>

<h3 id="financial-support">Financial Support</h3>

<p>Sponsorships help to keep this project sustainable, and buys time for the core developers to commit to the project. A recurring or one off sponsorship is a great way to help InvenTree development to continue at full steam!</p>

<p>The work undertaken to keep InvenTree running is done by a very small group of core developers, who do so in their spare time (and are not sponsored by their employers to work on InvenTree). If you benefit from the InvenTree project, please consider contributing to maintain vibrant development of this software!</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://polar.sh/inventree">Polar.sh</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/sponsors/inventree">GitHub</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>SchrodingersGat</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The InvenTree team is proud to announce the release of InvenTree version 0.17.0! This is the most significant release of InvenTree to date, with a huge number of new features, bug fixes, and improvements. We have closed out over 400 pull requests against this release milestone, and received contributions from multiple developers including seven new contributors.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">0.16.9 Release</title><link href="/blog/2024/11/30/0.16.9" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="0.16.9 Release" /><published>2024-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2024/11/30/0.16.9</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2024/11/30/0.16.9"><![CDATA[<h2 id="0169-release">0.16.9 Release</h2>

<p>We have just released version 0.16.9 which includes a number of patches and bug fixes.</p>

<h3 id="release-notes">Release Notes</h3>

<p>View the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/releases/tag/0.16.9">release notes</a> for more information.</p>]]></content><author><name>SchrodingersGat</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[0.16.9 Release]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">0.16.8 Release</title><link href="/blog/2024/11/07/0.16.8" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="0.16.8 Release" /><published>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2024/11/07/0.16.8</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2024/11/07/0.16.8"><![CDATA[<h2 id="0168-release">0.16.8 Release</h2>

<p>We have just released version 0.16.8 which includes a patch for a critical bug in the InvenTree package installer. We recommend that users upgrade to this version as soon as possible.</p>

<h3 id="missing-translation-files">Missing Translation Files</h3>

<p>Some users were experiencing reports of missing translation files when installing InvenTree using the package installer. The issue was identified and resolved in this release. Refer to the release notes (linked below) for more information.</p>

<h3 id="release-notes">Release Notes</h3>

<p>View the <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/releases/tag/0.16.8">release notes</a></p>]]></content><author><name>SchrodingersGat</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[0.16.8 Release]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">UI Roadmap - going 1.0</title><link href="/blog/2024/09/23/ui-roadmap" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UI Roadmap - going 1.0" /><published>2024-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2024/09/23/ui-roadmap</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2024/09/23/ui-roadmap"><![CDATA[<p>In August 2023 we announced <a href="/blog/2023/08/28/react">in a blog post</a> that we are working on a new user interface for InvenTree. This post is a follow-up to that announcement and provides an overview of the progress we have made so far and what we are planning to do next.
The most important information for you: the next release (0.17.0) will be the last with the old interface (CUI) as the default. The new interface (PUI) will be the default starting with the 0.18.0 release.<br />
The plan is to release 1.0 once PUI has all features ported, that will probably be the release after 0.18.0. 1.0 will not include CUI or the needed front- and backend code to support it.</p>

<p>Most of this article is probably only interesting for (plugin) developers, but we hope it gives you a good overview of what is happening.</p>

<h2 id="pui--cui---a-short-overview">PUI / CUI - A short overview</h2>

<p>The new interface is called PUI (Platform User Interface) and the old one CUI (Classic User Interface). PUI is built with React and is a single-page application. CUI is built with Django templates and uses a mixture of jQuery, templated JS and some libraries.
PUI is designed to be more consistent, use the API everywhere and support better testing (end-to-end, typing). The original blog post has more information on the <a href="/blog/2023/08/28/react#design-goals">design goals</a>.</p>

<h2 id="why-remove-cui">Why remove CUI?</h2>

<p>CUI has proven to be hard to understand for new contributors and hard to maintain in a consistent quality. Some common issues like cache invalidation, inconsistent rendering and hard-to-enforce permissions are easier to solve in PUI.
Therefore 1.0 will be PUI only. The compiled javascript, CSS and html files will be removed from the repository. CUI-only endpoints/tags will also be removed. Some HTML rendering will be kept as the report/label generation uses that.</p>

<p>This will probably remove around 2k files from the repo, around 370k lines. As of writing, we have 4.4k files and 2.4M lines in the repo.</p>

<h2 id="effect-on-plugins">Effect on plugins</h2>

<p>Plugins that render into the UI will need to be updated to work with PUI. This could affect you if your plugins use the mixins <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PanelMixin</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SettingsContentMixin</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NavigationMixin</code> or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">UrlsMixin</code>. Rendering into PUI is best done with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">UserInterfaceMixin</code> (available in 0.17.0) - which is actively expanded to support rendering more tightly integrated than <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PanelMixin</code> and CUI. For example <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/pull/8137">#8137</a> supports rendering custom template editors in PUI.</p>

<p>We will issue guidance regarding the transition of plugins into the new mechanisms before 1.0 goes to production.</p>

<h2 id="how-can-you-help">How can you help?</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Use the new UI - if you are on the 0.16.x release train your instance should already be serving it</li>
  <li>Report bugs - if you find something that is not working as expected please report it</li>
  <li>Report missing features - if you are missing something from CUI please report it (we have an EPIC<a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/issues/5212"> that tracks them</a>)</li>
  <li>Start looking into developing PUI and contributing - we use React and Mantine, widely used technologies</li>
  <li>Support the development - we have been developing PUI for over a year with more or less 3 people. Donations could help us spend more time or awarding bounties for features/design improvements.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-big-10">The big 1.0</h2>

<p>1.0 will be a big milestone for InvenTree. InvenTree has been running in the heart of many companies for years. The switch to PUI enables much safer work on the UI. The release number 1.0 signals that the last part of the system is now modernised and ready for the future. We are looking forward to it and hope you are too.</p>

<p>Switching to 1.0 will also mean that we will follow SemVer fully. Big breaking changes will only be in major releases, feature releases (1.0, 1.1, 1.2) will follow the SemVer rules. This will make it easier for some of our enterprise users who face backlash or difficulty because of the below 1.0 version number.</p>

<p>We are discussing a few more breaking changes in 1.0 - feel free to chime in on the dedicated issue <a href="https://github.com/inventree/InvenTree/issues/6417">#6417</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>matmair</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In August 2023 we announced in a blog post that we are working on a new user interface for InvenTree. This post is a follow-up to that announcement and provides an overview of the progress we have made so far and what we are planning to do next. The most important information for you: the next release (0.17.0) will be the last with the old interface (CUI) as the default. The new interface (PUI) will be the default starting with the 0.18.0 release. The plan is to release 1.0 once PUI has all features ported, that will probably be the release after 0.18.0. 1.0 will not include CUI or the needed front- and backend code to support it.]]></summary></entry></feed>